Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (II) 1820-1923
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Writtings, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Book Manuscripts, n.d. (Box 1-2)
    - Prose story, Fate Turns up the ease,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 11 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Prose story, Meatre,[by James Barron Hope]; set in Paris, n.d., 16 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Prose story, A Ship,[by James Barron Hope]., 11 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Untitled prose story [by James Barron Hope], opening line: "It was impossible to converse as...", 23 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Story begins in New York City, from which the main character is about to depart.
    - Book manuscript for Col. Cockney Hops, n.d., 76 pages. Chapters 1-6. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Book manuscript for Col. Cockney Hops, n.d., 71 pages. Chapters 7-9, 12, 13. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Essays, Addresses, and Plays, 1850-1871, n.d. (Box-folder 2:2-14)
    - Incomplete essay [by James Barron Hope], page 13 beginning "But if Englishmen in those days...", n.d., 4 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Pertains to European history.
    - Incomplete essay [by James Barron Hope] on American history, n.d., 6 pages. Pages 9 through 14. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Primarily on the Declaration of Independence.
    - Incomplete address [by James Barron Hope]; 1st page [page 29] begins "I shall now give you some account", n.d., 14 pages. Pages 29-42. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Possibly a part of the "Press and Printer's Devil."
    - Incomplete address [by James Barron Hope], beginning "Mr. Chairman, Gentlemen of the Institute, Ladies and Guests - Antithesis is ever suggestive...", n.d., 8 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      On the subject of Virginia history; compares the modern social system favorably with that of the eighteenth century
    - Incomplete address [by James Barron Hope], beginning on page 3 with "obtain a pecuniary consideration...", n.d., 4 pages. Pages 3-6. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      On the subject of American and European societies.
    - Incomplete play [by James Barron Hope]; first page [not originally 1st] begins "others princes-camp and court saw us...", n.d., 9 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Characters include Don Diego, Jon Alonso, Conrad, and Rhodolph.
    - Prose story [by James Barron Hope]; opening line: "Showing how the Doctor's hat blew off, and the Captain told his story....", n.d., 5 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Page from narrative history [in hand of James Barron Hope]; subject is War of 1812; stops in mid-sentence, n.d., 1 page. Fragment. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to the Patrick Henry Literary Association [in Richmond, Virginia]; begins: "Fellow citizens, Many years have fled and been entombed.. .", 4 July 1850., 16 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:3)
      James Barron Hope's first speech ever delivered.
    - Address [to a Virginian educational institution] [by James Barron Hope]; begins: "Six years ago, in the month of April," [1871]., 25 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Much of the speech relates to morality.
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] made at Yorktown, Virginia, 19 October [18]81., 36 pages. 1st page is missing. AMs. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Includes references to the earlier celebration of the 250th anniversary of the Jamestown Settlement; this was given at the Yorktown Centennial celebration.
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to a civic governmental assembly; written while Superintendent of Norfolk schools; opens: "Mr. Prost and Gentlemen, In so grave a matter as the present.. .", [ca. April 1886]., 24 pages. Df of AMs. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Mentions the appropriation of public funds.
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to a North Carolinian organization; opens with: "Mr. President and Gentlemen," [post 1865]. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Last page [?] seems inconclusive; main subjects are history and government.
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] [to a Young Ladies' School Graduation]; 1st page missing; 2nd page begins: "cheeks of the hue of roses...", [post 1865]., 13 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Address to the Orphan's Asylum in Richmond, [Virginia], [by James Barron Hope], [post 1865]., 26 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to Hollins Institute, on the subject of charity, n.d., 19 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to a Virginia Organization; inspirational account of Virginia history, n.d., 28 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] on the modes by which the United States expanded; first line: "The growth of this Republic is a familiar topic", n.d., 17 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope] to a Virginian, all-male Institute; begins: "Mr. Chairman, Gentlemen of the Institute, Ladies and Gentlemen: Antitheses is ever suggestive", n.d., 48 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Address [by James Barron Hope], A Study in Comparative Geography, Illustrated by Ideal Maps, with a Commercial Application,n.d., 40 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 2:14)
      Concerns the commercial history of Virginia.
  Series 3: Miscellaneous Materials
- Miscellaneous Materials, 1820-1923, n.d. (Box-folder 2:15-19)
  - A. K. S., [?], Maryland, to [James Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], 25 August 1879., 3 pages. Cy of M. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Tribute by unknown woman to his work Under The Empire.
    Bears ALS from Kensey Johns, Sudley, [Maryland], to [James Barron] Hope, Norfolk, [Virginia]; Above tribute is by a lady friend of his; he may print it in The Landmark, or throw it away; greetings to the family.
  - "To Miss Jane Barron Hope," [by Hugh Blair Grigsby], [Charlotte County, Virginia?], [ante 1882]., 1 page. Poem. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - "My Powhatan Pipe," by J[ohn] Esten Cooke,[Boyce?], Virginia, 30 May 1885., 4 pages. AmsS. Poem. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Excerpt from Alexander von Humboldt's, New Spain, n.d., 8 pages. Cy of Ms. (Box-folder 2:15)
    The potato from a historical point of view; written in hand of James Barron Hope.
  - "A Proclamation By the Commandr and Commissionrs of Accomack," n.d., 1 page. Cy of D. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Following the beheading of Charles I this proclamation affirmed the loyalty of the authors to Charles II; signed [in the original] by Edm: Matthews Clc. Cur. [original is probably in Accomack County records].
  - Excerpts from Howison's History of Virginia,n.d., 1 page. Cy of Ms. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Concerns religious laws in Virginia; written in hand of James Barron Hope.
  - Brief biography of James Baron Hope, unsigned, n.d., 4 pages. Ms. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Apparently intended to accompany the poem Lioni Di Monota; mentions his attendance of, and B. A. degree from, the College of William and Mary.
  - Deed for sale of land by George and Elisabeth Camp to Commodore James Barron; $300 in exchange for a lot in Hampton, Virginia, 1 January 1839., 4 pages. DS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Certificate of Ja[me]s Barron Hope as member of the Norfolk Mexican Veteran Association, signed by Ja[me]s [F.?] Milligan and Jno. D. Simms, 30 March 1881., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Certificate of J[ames] Barron Hope as City Superintendent of Schools for Norfolk, Virginia, signed by Fitzhugh Lee and Geo[rge] W. Harveyhurst[?], 30 January 1886., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Certificate of Ja[me]s Barron Hope as City Superintendent of Schools for Norfolk, Virginia, signed by Fitzhugh Lee and L. R. Holland [?], 15 May 1886., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Preamble and Resolutions mourning the death of James Barron Hope, by the Pickett-Buchanan Camp of Confederate Veterans of Norfolk, Virginia, of which he was a member; signed by Rev. B. D. Tucker, Judge T. S. Garnett, Col. L. D. Starke, M. Glennan, and T. B. Jackson, 20 September 1887., 2 pages. Cy of D. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Resolutions following the death of James Barron Hope by the "A. F. V. A. M." organization, of which he was a member; signed by S[amuel] P[reston] Moore[?], W[illia]m R. Galt, W[illia]m H. Burroughs, and Walter H. Taylor, 3 October [1887]., 2 pages. Cy of D. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Newspaper article with the heading "Georgetown"; describes the duel which took place on Wednesday, March 22, 1820 between Commodores Stephen Decatur and James Barron, 24 March 1820., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Commodore Decatur was mortally wounded, while Commodore Barron was seriously wounded; contains the funeral procession for Commodore Decatur.
  - Address given before the Neotrophian Society of the Hampton Academy, by James Barron Hope, 25 July 1856., 15 pages. PM. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Flyer, "Down With Mahone Interference!", [September 1874]., 1 page. PM. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Accusing Mahone of plotting to control Richmond, and spreading lies concerning [Bradley] Johnson; [relates to near duel, in which James Barron Hope was Mahone's second].
  - Newspaper clipping of the New York Herald describing the events concerning the aborted duel; mentions James Barron Hope, 3 October 1874., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Newspaper article, The Cities of Virginia,28 April 1880., 2 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Describing James Barron Hope's speech on that subject on the previous night in Association Hall, [Richmond]; [article is from the Richmond State].
  - Newspaper heading, For The House Of Delegates,6 November 1883., 2 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Recommendations for the above offices; article urging that no alcoholic beverages be consumed around election time; article stressing [William] Mahone's faults, which stirs up racist fears and seeks to belittle [Mahone].
  - Newspaper article, Charges Against Judge Godwin, listing supposed wrongdoings by the judge, primarily relating to nepotism, [1883?]., 1 page. NswCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Newspaper article, Mahoneism, What We May Expect Under Mahone Rule,[November 1883?]., 4 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Address by Danville, [Virginia] merchants and businessmen "to the White Men of Virginia"; accuses Mahone of favoring Negroes over whites; urges that conservative Democrats be voted for.
  - Newspaper article, Mayor Wm. Lamb Restrained,[November 1883]., 2 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Mayor of Norfolk barred from erecting barricades at the polls on election day.
    Includes newspaper article, Riot In Danville; Negroes fought whites; several Negroes killed. 1 page. Nwscl.
  - "Extracts from Diary of Janey Hope;" a parade at which James Barron Hope was honored, 20 November 1883., 2 pages. Ms. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Note by [Janey Hope Marr]; her father's well-received prose poem, 23 June [18]84., 2 pages. Fragment. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Note by [Janey Hope Marr]; her father's attendance of the National Democratic Convention in Chicago, 8 July 1884. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Card and ribbon from national Democratic Convention in Chicago; James Barron Hope was a delegate, 8 July 1884. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Typed diary entry by [Janey Hope Marr]; glad that a Democratic President, Grover Cleveland, has been elected, 9 November 1884., 1 page. TMs. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Postcard to James Barron Hope, announcing a meeting for the Presidential Committee on Reception; signed by W[illiam] W[ilson] Corcoran,2 February 1885., 1 page. ACS. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Booklet from President Cleveland's Inauguration, 4 March 1885., 24 pages. PM. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Newspaper article, begins: We here give the notes from which he spoke; notes from a speech given by [James Barron] Hope on George Washington, [ante 15 September 1887]., 7 pages. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Newspaper article with the heading, Dueling In The Old Navy,16 January 1910., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Discloses the facts of the Hope-Jones duel and of some other affairs; blames the duel on Jones' second.
  - Newspaper article, Hope's Landmark,4 January 1912., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    James Barron Hope's association with the Norfolk Landmark and the Norfolk Virginian Pilot.
  - Newspaper article announcing the death of Annie Beverley Whiting Hope, widow of James Barron Hope; she lived to age 95; [Norfolk, Virginia newspaper?], [1 June 1920]., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Newspaper article, Norfolk - Fifty Years Ago, From the Norfolk Virginian, October 2, 1873,[2 October 1923]., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Detailed the presentation of a gold pencil to James Barron Hope by the staff [of the Norfolk Landmark].
  - Newspaper article, Letters Written During A Cruise In the West Indies, from the Petersburg, [Virginia], South-Side Democrat,n.d., 1 page. NwsCl. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Narrates the arrival of the U. S. Sloop-of-War, Spray, at a port in the Caribbean, and the officers' desire to go on shore.
  - Newspaper article, In Memoriam - Honors To Confederate Dead, in Norfolk Virginian,19 June 1884., 2 pages. PM. (Box-folder 2:18)
    Norfolk's first Memorial Day; James Barron Hope was the Commander of the Pickett-Buchanan Camp of Confederate Veterans.
  - Miscellaneous fragments and envelope. (Box-folder 2:19)